Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Photographs PHOTOS.031
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Photographs
1979-2008
1979-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PHOTOS.031
0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box
The Tamiment Library was originally founded in 1906 as part of the Rand School for Social Science, a pioneering workers education school sponsored by the American Socialist Society. In 1963 New York University acquired the Library. In 1977, the Tamiment Institute, New York University, and the New York City Central Labor Council founded the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives in order to preserve the historical records of the New York City labor movement. With the support of Harry Van Arsdale, president of the Central Labor Council, the Wagner became the designated repository of the Central Labor Council's member unions and affiliated organizations. The collection documents the activities and projects of the Tamiment Library / Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, as well as its publicity efforts. Included are photographs of exhibition openings, anniversary celebrations, receptions and other events.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Photographs in this collection were created by Tamiment Library and Tamiment Library staff. Photos in this collection were originally separated into two collections, The Tamiment Library Photographs (PHOTOS 031) and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Photographs (PHOTOS 58), which were later combined into one collection, the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Photographs (PHOTOS 031). The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1950.199, 2011.106, NPA.1997.031, NPA.2000.217, NPA.2000.245, NPA.2000.250, NPA.2000.311, NPA.2000.314, NPA.2000.323, NPA.2000.041, NPA.2001.011, NPA.2002.012, NPA.2003.029, NPA.2003.030, NPA.2003.041, NPA.2004.064, NPA.2004.068, NPA.2004.072, NPA.2004.082, NPA.2005.035, NPA.2005.048, NPA.2005.084, NPA.2005.161, NPA.2006.016.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Tamiment Library was originally founded in 1906 as part of the Rand School for Social Science, a pioneering workers education school sponsored by the American Socialist Society. In 1917 the school moved to 7 East 15th Street near Union Square where it remained for almost fifty-five years. The Rand School was modeled after the Socialist People's Houses in Europe and it soon became a cultural and educational center for the Left in New York.
The Library was named the Meyer London Library after the long-time Socialist who represented the Lower East Side of Manhattan. Teachers included Scott Nearing and Betrand Russell, who lost teaching positions because of their political beliefs. Charles and Mary Beard were also members of the faculty.
In the early years of the twentieth century the Rand School Library was one of the few repositories in the country collecting materials relating to the history of labor and socialism. The Library actively solicited books, periodicals, pamphlets, and archival material describing the history of the labor and progressive movements. Many of the early leaders of the Socialist Party like Eugene Debs, J.B.S. Hardman, Meyer London, and Harry Laidler donated collections of papers to the Library.
In addition to supporting the teaching programs of the Rand School, the Meyer London Library provided research materials that the New York labor movement needed for contract negotiations, grievances, and arbitration proceedings. It also offered shop steward training, public lectures, theatre and musical productions.
The Rand School and its Meyer London Library were often harassed and attacked by police and state troopers. In 1919 over 75 law enforcement officers, under the auspices of the New York State Lusk Committee, raided the school, seizing documents and library materials that were never returned.
After World War II when many returning soldiers began to take advantage of the G.I. Bill of Rights to finance their college educations, the Rand School fell on hard times as enrollments dropped dramatically. In 1956 Camp Tamiment, a socialist summer camp in Pennsylvania's Pocono Mountains, purchased the Rand School and its library. It closed the school and attempted to integrate its educational and cultural programs into the Tamiment Institute. The Library was renamed the Ben Josephson Library.
In 1963 New York University acquired the Library. In 1977, the Tamiment Institute, New York University, and the New York City Central Labor Council founded the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives in order to preserve the historical records of the New York City labor movement. With the support of Harry Van Arsdale, president of the Central Labor Council, the Wagner became the designated repository of the Central Labor Council's member unions and affiliated organizations.
Scope and Content Note
The collection documents the activities and projects of the Tamiment Library / Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, as well as its publicity efforts. Included are photographs of exhibition openings, anniversary celebrations, receptions and other events, as well as members of the Library and Archives staff.
Labor leaders |z United States |v Archives.; Labor movement -- New York (State) -- New York -- History; Exhibitions.; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York -- History -- 20th century.; Photographs.; Social Service Employees Union. Local 371; International Union, United Automobile, Aerospace, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America. District 65; American Federation of Musicians; Stewardesses for Women's Rights; Tamiment Playhouse; Bernhardt, Debra E.; Communications Workers of America; AFSCME. District Council 37 (New York, N.Y.); Roth, Ed
- American Federation of Musicians, Feb 27, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Social Service Employees Union Reception, Feb 27, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- United Automobile Workers of America, District 65 Reception, Oct 2, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Preserving NY Labor Heritage (Slideshow Script), Nov 13, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Preserving NY Labor Heritage, Apr 26, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Wagner Labor Archives, 5th Anniversary, Nov 17, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Wagner Labor Archives, 6th Anniversary, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Stewardesses for Women's Rights Collection Opening, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Wagner Labor Archives, 10th Anniversary, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Pictures of Our Lives" Exhibit, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Wagner Labor Archives, 15th Anniversary, Apr 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Tamiment Playhouse Exhibit: "Every Week a Broadway Review", Oct 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- David Montgoemery Presentation, Feb 24, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Communication Workers of America Headquarters, circa 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- National Archives Annual Report, Aug 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- District Council 37: Gallery Talk ("Ordinary People, Extrodinary Lives"), Nov 4, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Morton Bahr Book Signing, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Debra E. Bernhardt Annual Archives Award, Nov 8, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives Exhibit (Bobst Library Atrium), Mar 2008 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Debra Bernhardt (Miscellaneous), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Ed Roth "Pillar of Labor" Memorial, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- New Yorkers at Work, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
- New Yorkers at Work: Study Guide, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Wagner Labor Archives: "Rights as Workers", undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Photos, negatives, 1989-2004 (Box 2, Folder 1-23)